Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is, what
daf דף daf are we today? It is daf דף daf Tet-Zayin
טז, Tet-Zayin, I believe? Yes, it is Tet-Zayin טז, Tet-Zayin, and we
pick up at the bottom of Tet-Vav Amud Bet טו
עמוד ב. Tet-Vav Amud Bet. And the mishna משנה mishna talked about
a caravan that encamped right before Shabbos שבת Shabbos and they built
for themselves a wall out of the various, you know, baggage that
they had, out of the various things that they had on their
animals and so on, and they made piles of it and they
made a camp, and that can count as long as the gaps
in the walls, because they didn't, you know, make everything a wall,
is not greater than the—is not greater than the standing part.
And they don't need a kora קורה kora on top between the
two?
These are walls. This is not—if they would need a kora קורה
kora if they only did three walls. This is presumably that they
did all four walls.
So thank you very much. So, so this led the Gemara גמרא
Gemara to a discussion about what if it is exactly equal, half
and half? And here there was a debate between Rav Papa רב
פפא Rav Papa and Rav Huna רב הונא. Rav Huna. Rav Papa
רב פפא Rav Papa said that that's okay, half and half, and
Rav Huna רב הונא Rav Huna said it's not good, and the
debate was this is paratz k'omed פרוץ כעומד, paratz k'omed, the gaps
part is equal to the walled part. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara
framed this, well first it interestingly used the phrase hachi agmurei machr'na
l'Moshe הכי אגמורי מכרנא למשה. hachi agmurei machr'na l'Moshe. This is what
God taught Moshe משה, Moshe, but which is interesting, reflecting the idea
that this is halakha l'Moshe miSinai הלכה למשה מסיני. halakha l'Moshe miSinai.
But ultimately it became a question of which thing do you give
the criteria for? If you say the criteria is given for what
you need it to be kosher כשר, kosher, in order to be
kosher כשר kosher the majority has to be walled. So then if
it's 50-50 it's no good, that's Rav Huna's רב הונא's Rav Huna
position. Or you could say that the criteria is given—criterion is given
for the invalidity, the psul פסול. psul. It's invalid if the majority
is exposed and in that case 50-50 would be okay. And again,
as I said at the end of the day yesterday on Shabbos
שבת, Shabbos, that this often is an issue of whether are you
defining what makes it what, you know, what's needed to make it
good or what's needed to make it not good? And obviously there's
a difference because, I mean, you could always say things in the
exact reverse, but usually if you're going to define what's positively needed
to make it good, that's going to create a high criteria because
you assume it's not good and you need to meet these criteria
to make it good. If you say here's what you need to
make it invalid, that'll assume that it'll be a lower criteria to
be okay because the assumption is it's okay and only when something
is, you know, reaches a certain level does it become invalid. I'll
give you just here one other like example. Let's say you said
for an etrog אתרוג etrog to be kosher כשר, kosher, it has
to be hadar הדר, hadar, it has to be beautiful, aesthetic. That's
one way of saying it. Another way you could say is etrog
אתרוג etrog is invalid if it's not hadar הדר. hadar. Okay, now
sounds like it's saying the same thing but at a certain level
it's not because one is saying you have to basically prove to
me it's beautiful if you want to make it valid, and the
other basically is saying you have to prove to me it's not
beautiful and there's a gap between beautiful and not, you know, whatever,
there's that middle space and that exactly is what's sort of being
debated here. So let's take a look now at the Gemara's גמרא's
Gemara going to try to prove it. Tnan תנן, Tnan, we are
about 10 lines from the bottom, line starts with the word Rachmana
רחמנא, Rachmana, end of the line. Tnan תנן, Tnan, we taught in
our mishna משנה. mishna. So our mishna's משנה's mishna around where this
debate is going to circle. So we taught in our mishna משנה
mishna v'lo yehu pirtzot yiterot al habinyan ולא יהיו פירצות יתירות על
הבנין. v'lo yehu pirtzot yiterot al habinyan. The gaps should not be
more than the structured part when they made this wall, this caravan
that encamped.
So ha הא, ha, that sounds like k'binyan כבנין, k'binyan, if it's
exactly 50-50, mutar מותר mutar is permissible. So that's a proof to
Rav Papa רב פפא Rav Papa that it's only when it's too
big is the gaps are too large it's invalid. So the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says no, lo teima ha k'binyan mutar לא תימא הא
כבנין מותר. lo teima ha k'binyan mutar. It doesn't mean that if
it's 50-50, if it's exactly equal, it's permissible. Ela eima im binyan
yater al hapirtza mutar אלא אימא אם בנין יתר על הפירצה מותר.
ela eima im binyan yater al hapirtza mutar. That if—no, that if
it's more of the structure than the gaps, that's when it is
permissible. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says what do you mean? Aval
k'binyan mai אבל כבנין מאי, Aval k'binyan mai, so you would say
then what would you say if it was equal? Assur אסור, Assur,
forbidden. I hachi אי הכי, I hachi, so then say that lisni
לתני lisni lo yehu pirtzot k'binyan לא יהיו פירצות כבנין, lo yehu
pirtzot k'binyan, that the gaps should not be as big as the
structure. Why does it say that they should not be bigger than
the structure? Gemara גמרא Gemara says kashya קשיא, kashya, alright, it's difficult.
Not, you know, sounds like a pretty good proof.
But again the question all along by all of the evidence is
is that how much are the—are we going to assume the mishnayot
משניות mishnayot and the braitot ברייתות braitot that we're going to bring
are being precise or not precise? You know, I mean, you have
to start by saying I want to know what the story is
if it's exactly 50-50. If you generally assume, A, you can't measure
that way, B, it's not a case, you know, that precise, B,
it's not a case that's going to ever that's going to occur
very likely, so you might not be so precise. Sometimes you'll say
if it's gaps are too good it's invalid, sometimes you'll say if
there's more standing stuff it is valid and maybe there's some imprecision
going on here. So that's part of the ongoing question. But certainly
the simple sense of our mishna משנה mishna says that if gaps
are too big it's invalid, sounds like 50-50 it's okay. Ta shma
תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear, says the Gemara גמרא, Gemara,
a mishna משנה mishna from Sukkah סוכה. Sukkah. המכסכך סוכתו בשפודין או
בארוכות המטה, Hamesaker sukaso bishpudin o bearuchos hamitah, if you make a
roof on your סוכה Sukkah with like bars of metal or with
like the legs of a bed, so these things are invalid because
they're not, either they're a כלי kli or they're not made or
they're not from a גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, they don't grow from
the ground. So and so you alternate between rows of סכך s'chach
and metal bars. So אם יש ריווח ביניהם כמותן, im yesh revach
beinehem kemosan, if the gap between the כשר סכך kosher s'chach is
equal to the width of the כשר סכך, kosher s'chach, כשרה, kesherah,
it's valid. So basically the width of the invalid is equal to
the width of the valid, you know, as you alternate these strips,
then it's okay. So again you see it says if it's equal
it's valid, a pretty good proof to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Now
of course first of all you could say since when does, it's
one thing to compare walls from different areas of הלכה, halacha, but
here you're talking about roofs, not walls. And especially if the idea
of a roof is like צילתו מרובה מחמתו, tzilaso merubah mechamaso, you
know it should provide shade, so just because it's exactly equal on
top does that provide more shade on the bottom or less shade
on the bottom? You know, that's not necessarily true that what it
is on the top determines the shade it's going to provide on
the bottom. So it's very strange that the גמרא Gemara assumes that
the exact same sort of definitions would apply by the roof that
would apply by a wall. But anyway let's see what the גמרא
Gemara answers. So the גמרא Gemara says so there you see equal
is okay. הכא במאי עסקינן כשנכנס ויוצא. Hacha bemai askinan keshenichnas veyotze.
No, it doesn't mean equal is okay. It means that you can
pull the good סכך s'chach in and out easily between the gaps
of the bad סכך. s'chach. So if you can insert the good
סכך s'chach of an equal width easily into the gaps, the סכך
s'chach of an equal width, it means that the actual width of
the gaps that you're inserting the good סכך s'chach is slightly larger.
Okay, so the גמרא. Gemara. You don't get it? If I want
to say if this is my bad סכך s'chach and I wanted
to say if the gap here is equal to this then it's
okay because I can put good סכך s'chach in. So what I'm
saying is really no, if I can take an equal width of
good סכך s'chach and insert it easily into the gap, the gap
has to be a little bit bigger. Doesn't that make it worse
then you have less good סכך? s'chach? No
no no, this is the bad סכך. s'chach. The gap is the
width I'm inserting the good סכך, s'chach, okay? So it doesn't literally
mean that it's equal, it means it's a gap big enough that
I can easily insert the good סכך s'chach into.
So the גמרא Gemara says והא אפשר לצמצם? veha efshar litzamtzem?
So it's all question how to read this next line, I'll read
it the way רש''י Rashi reads it. So the גמרא Gemara says
but what do you mean? Why would it have to give the
example, you're saying that when it says equal it really means a
little bit bigger. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that the reason you're
saying a little bit bigger is because it's impossible to precisely measure.
So the גמרא Gemara says but you can precisely measure. So again
it's another way of saying why did it say equal if it
meant bigger? So אמר רב אמי במעדיף. amar Rav Ami bema'adif.
It's true, it is possible to exactly measure, but the whole point
is that you are intentionally making it, this is the way רש''י
Rashi reads it, intentionally making the gap a little bit bigger in
order so that you can actually have more כשר סכך. kosher s'chach.
So it says equal but it doesn't mean equal, it means that
you can insert an equal amount of סכך s'chach easily, which means
that the gap is actually a little bit bigger.
רבא אמר אם היו נתונים ערב נותן שתי שתי נותן ערב. Rava
amar im hayu nesunim erev nosen shesi shesi nosen erev. If it
was done widthwise do it lengthwise, lengthwise you do it widthwise, which
means yes it's true, the gap here only has to be where
you're going to put the כשר סכך, kosher s'chach, only has to
be equal to the size of the פסול סכך. pasul s'chach. But
you're not putting the כשר סכך kosher s'chach in like this, you're
putting the כשר סכך kosher s'chach in like this. So you know,
so you're going in the opposite direction. So if you're going in
the opposite direction, it's supporting itself on the פסול סכך, pasul s'chach,
which means it's actually a little bit more than the פסול סכך.
pasul s'chach. Now it's interesting, not more than it actually shades because
it's overlapping, but somehow the גמרא Gemara feels that that is a
sufficient answer. So again, the whole discussion on סכך s'chach is quite
strange because it seems to ignore the unique concerns about סכך s'chach
about providing shade and so on. But anyway the simple meat of
that is that it's equal, but the גמרא Gemara says it might
not be equal, maybe it means that it's somewhat overlapping or has
somewhat extra space and therefore it actually is more כשר סכך. kosher
s'chach. תא שמע, Tashma, come here says the גמרא Gemara back to
something that's a little more familiar. שיירא שחנתה בבקעה, shayara shechantah bevikah,
if you had a caravan that encamped in a valley, והקיפוה vehekifuha
and this is basically our משנה, Mishnah, it's just a little bit
more colorful, והקיפוה בגמלים vehekifuha begamalim and you sort of had camels
standing all around to be your walls. Of course camels have like
a pretty
long body so there's got to be a lot of gap there.
Anyway, באוכפות, beuchafos, or you actually use the saddles, בעביטים ba'avitim with
an עביט. avit. An עביט avit is sometimes a chamber pot, but
רש''י Rashi here says that an עביט avit is a
some cloth that goes underneath the or pillow that goes underneath the
saddle.
בשלפין, bishlifin, in
your
saddlebags or
you
know your luggage. Exactly. מטלטלין בתוכה. metaltalin betocha. Then you could carry
in it, ובלבד uvilvad with a condition שלא יהיה בין גמל לגמל
כמלא גמל, shelo yihiyeh bein gamal legamal kimlo gamal, between one camel
and the other should not be the width of a camel. And
again it's quite funny because, like, what about the legs of the
camel? I don't get exactly how that's working, but anyway, because there's
a lot of gap underneath the camel. ובין אוכף לאוכף כמלא אוכף,
uvein ukaf le'ukaf kimlo ukaf, or between one saddle and another like
the width of a saddle, ובין אביט לאביט כמלא אביט, uvein avit
le'avit kimlo avit, and between one again pillow and another, the width.
So basically, it says you cannot have equal to the width, which
sounds like when the gaps are equal, it sounds like it's no
good. So this is a proof like רב הונא Rav Huna that
when the gaps are equal, it's no good.
So the גמרא Gemara says, now it's saying it's to defend רב
פפא, Rav Pappa, הכא נמי כשנכנס ויוצא. hacha nami keshnichnas veyotze. When
it says if you have an equal-sized gap, it's no good, it
doesn't literally mean equal. It means it's big enough that you could
easily fit in something of the same size, which means that the
gap is actually slightly larger. Okay, so getting out of the proofs
by basically saying that the משניות mishnayot here are being or ברייתות
braitot are being imprecise. תא שמע, ta shema, come in here.
This is by כלאים. kilayim. נמצאת אתה אומר, nimtzata ata omer, says
the, it says the תוספתא, Tosefta, you can, you'll if you look
at it, you'll see that there are שלוש מידות במחיצות, shalosh midot
bimechitzot, there are three different categories of מחיצות mechitzot when it comes
to כלאים. kilayim. Now, as you know, and as we've talked before,
by כלאים, kilayim, you can plant different types of seeds even right
next to each other if they're divided by a מחיצה. mechitza. So
what defines a מחיצה mechitza if it has walls?
So כל שהוא פחות משלושה, kol shehu pachot mishlosha, if the actual
wall itself is less than
three, okay, so I'll draw something.
Okay, fine.
So
one scenario here is that you're going to be having the sections
of the wall, I don't know, here you have wheat
and here you have the grapes and here you have a wall
between them. So if the sections of the wall with gaps, okay,
so if the sections of the wall are less than three, okay,
2.9 or whatever, now here,
or whatever they are, they can be anywhere from .1 to 2.9,
okay. These are if those are the sections of the walls, what
do you need to make it good? Well, if the gap here
is three, it's obviously going to be invalid. Why is it going
to be invalid? Because if it's three, you can't say לבוד, lavud,
and if it's three, it's going to be the gaps are going
to be bigger than the wall. But if these gaps are less
than three, okay, if these gaps are less than three, then you
can say לבוד. lavud. And since you can say לבוד, lavud, actually,
these sections can be actually tiny. Oh shoot, I used
dry erase. I wondered why it was coming out so well. All
right, anyway, I'll have to I think... if these gaps are less
than three, then this can be even .1, right? Because even if
these things are very tiny, because of לבוד lavud it's like it's
continuous. Okay, so the first, that's great, that is example number one.
It says כל שהוא פחות משלושה, kol shehu pachot mishlosha, if the
actual sections of the wall are less than three, צריך שלא יהיה
בין זה לזה שלושה. tzarich shelo yihiyeh bein zeh lezeh shlosha. It
has to be it has to be less than שלושה shlosha between
them, כדי שלא יזדקר הגדי בבת ראש. kedei shelo yizdaker hagadi bevbat
rosh.
Okay, with that again, that the kid goat cannot go through it
easily, you know? So that defines לבוד. lavud. So if it's
so criteria number one is that you can if you have the
sections less than three, then as long as the gaps are less
than three, even if the sections are tiny, you're fine and everything
is okay. That's category number one. מג' ועד ד', migeemel ve'ad daled,
let's say, however, the sections of the
wall are between three to four טפחים. tefachim. צריך שלא יהיה בין
זה לזה כמלאו. tzarich shelo yihiyeh bein zeh lezeh kimlo'o.
Now, obviously, if it's less than three, the gaps are always okay.
But here you actually have more space that you can have of
the gaps, as long as it's not equal to the actual size
of the sections, you're okay. כדי שלא יהיה פרוץ כעומד. kedei shelo
yihiyeh parutz ke'omed. And now here it's quite clear, it seems to
be like רב הונא. Rav Huna. It says there cannot be a
gap equal to the size of the partition, and in order and
here it actually uses the phrase פרוץ כעומד parutz ke'omed in order
that the gap should not be equal to the partition, and it
seems very clear that it's labeling פרוץ כעומד parutz ke'omed as invalid,
which is רב הונא. Rav Huna. But then, of course, it immediately
reverses itself. אם היה פרוץ מרובה על העומד, im hayah parutz merubeh
al ha'omed, and if the gap was bigger, אף כנגד העומד אסור,
af keneged ha'omed assur, then everything is forbidden even opposite the partition
itself. So first of all, that's going to be the key line.
It says don't allow it to be equal. because if it's bigger
it's a problem. So what is it? Is it a problem when
it's equal or is it a problem when it's bigger? But in
terms by the way of the הלכה halacha here, if these things
are between three and four,
okay, if these are between three to four, three to four, right,
if that's the size of these things, then then this has to
be, you know, has to be smaller, right,
smaller than the partition. Okay, as long as the gaps are smaller
than the partition, it's okay. So then you have the majority because
then you have most of it is, you know, is considered walls.
So what makes this though a second category? Because when that is
not satisfied, if the gaps are bigger, then then even the space
opposite the partition itself, even the space exactly immediate opposite the partition
is no good. None of it is good when those gaps are
bigger. Since each wall here is less than four טפחים, tfachim, it
does not have significance, and when therefore by itself, and therefore when
the gaps are bigger, everything is considered, it's all invalid, nothing nothing
is okay. So that's category number two. And now let's see what
category number three is. נפרצה, nifretzah, where are we, ואם היה עומד
מרובה על הפרוץ, v'im hayah omed merubah al haparutz, מארבע טפחים עד
עשר
אמות, me'arba tfachim ad eser amot,
from four טפחים tfachim to ten אמות, amot, צריך שלא יהא בין
זה לזה כמלואו, tzarich shelo yehei bein zeh lazeh kemlo'o, same issue,
you cannot have an equal sized gap to the size of the
partition, שלא יהא פרוץ כעומד, shelo yehei parutz k'omed, because then you'll
have equal gap to partition and that's invalid, again seemingly that the
equal is the problem. And now the second, now when it repeats
it here at least it's consistent, ואם היה פרוץ כעומד, v'im hayah
parutz k'omed,
and if the gap is equal to the partition. So now it's
said three times the problem is when it's equal, only once it
said the problem is when the gap is larger. But if the
gap is equal to the standing part, ואם היה פרוץ כעומד, v'im
hayah parutz k'omed, where was, where was, I lost my place, hold
on, שלא יהא פרוץ כעומד ואם היה פרוץ כעומד כנגד העומד מותר
כנגד הפרוץ אסור, shelo yehei parutz k'omed v'im hayah parutz k'omed k'neged
ha'omed muttar k'neged haparutz assur,
and if it's equal then then it is opposite the gap is
no good, but opposite the partition is okay. So here's the basic
way in which this is a different הלכה, halacha, okay? If it
was, if here you had not between three and four, but if
here you had anywhere from ארבעה טפחים עד עשרה אמות, arba'ah tfachim
ad asarah amot, okay, so it's basically
greater than four, and all of these partitions are
greater than
four, each partition is significant by itself, and even if it gets
isolated from the other partition because the gap is greater, at least
the space opposite the partition is okay. So anything planted opposite the
gap is no good, but opposite the partition is okay. The upshot
of all of this is is that what? Is that three times
it repeats you can't have the gap equal to the partition. The
different categories are if the partition is less than four, then opposite
the partition is no good, the partition by itself does not have
any status. If the partition is four טפחים tfachim or bigger, then
opposite the partition, even when it's standing by itself, remains okay, okay.
Then it goes on to say מותר כנגד הפרוץ אסור, muttar k'neged
haparutz assur, ואם היה עומד מרובה על הפרוץ, v'im hayah omed merubah
al haparutz,
if of course there's more partition than there is gap, again you
need more partition than gap, אף כנגד הפרוץ מותר, af k'neged haparutz
muttar, then even opposite the gap is okay. So that's why basically
you have three types of categories. What are the three categories? Category
number one is even opposite the partition is no good when the
partition is less than four, then it's not significant by itself. Category
number two is opposite the partition is good, not opposite the gap.
That's when the gaps are too big, but the partition is four
or bigger, then the partition is significant by even though standing by
itself and opposite the partition is okay. Category number three is even
opposite the gaps are okay. When is that true? When there's more
partition than gap, well then it's considered like it's entirely walled and
even opposite the gaps are okay. So three different categories: even opposite
the gaps is no good, opposite the gaps is good,
even opposite the partition is no good, category one, category two opposite
the partition is good, opposite the gaps is no good, and category
three is even opposite the gap is good. Okay now it ends
by saying היו שם קנים הדוקרנים, hayu sham kanim hadukranim, if you
had sort of like smooth posts that are stuck in, you know,
to cover the gap, I skipped a line, נפרצה ביתר מעשר, nifretzah
beyoter me'eser, if a gap is more than ten אמות, amot, אסור,
assur, that's always a problem even if you have equal size or
greater partition. But that's a pass. take that the gap more than
ten is a problem. היו שם קנים הדוקרנים, Hayu sham kanim hadukranim,
however, if you have posts inserted into the ground, ועשה להן פאה
מלמעלה v'asah lahen peah milmalah and you make a string above, אפילו
ביותר מעשר מותר afilu biyoter mei-eser mutar then even more than ten
big is okay. We quoted this before, this is the idea of
a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach more than ten. Okay, but anyway we
had the three categories and the upshot was, multiple times repeated, you
cannot have a gap equal to the partition. So the Gemara says,
so it's a pretty good proof. So the Gemara says, תני מיהת
tani miat we teach from all of, nevertheless, the point to emphasize
is, we teach רישא מג' ועד ד' ובלבד שלא יהא בין זו
לזו כמלואו reisha migimel v'ad daled uvilvad shelo yehei bein zu l'zu
kemilo that when you have things between three and four, as long
as you don't have between this and this equal to the size
of the partition. So you see equal to the size of the
partition is no good. תיובתא דרב פפא, tiyuvta d'Rav Pappa, a contradiction
to Rav Pappa, it makes it clear that equal is no good.
אמר לך רב פפא, amar lach Rav Pappa, so Rav Pappa will
say back to you, מאי לאו נכנס ויוצא, mai lav nichnas v'yotzei,
like the old standard answer. When it says equal it's no good,
it means equal with an easy way to move an equal size
in and out, which really means larger than equal. And the Gemara
says, הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra,
and the Gemara says actually that makes sense because there's one line
in this בריתא beraisa that sounded like Rav Pappa. Cause the there
was one line there that said, yeah I know, three of the
times it says it can't be equal, but once it says it
can't be greater. דקתני d'katni because once we said אם היה פרוץ
מרובה על העומד im hayah parutz merubah al ha'omed if the gap
was greater, אף כנגד העומד אסור af k'neged ha'omed assur then it's
opposite even opposite the partition. הא כי עומד מותר, ha ki omed
mutar, it's that one line made it sound that if it was
equal it's okay. שמע מינה, shma mina, so the Gemara says that's
a good point, that there's some imprecision going on in this בריתא.
beraisa. Three times it says it can't be equal, the gap, but
once it says it can't be bigger. So Rav Pappa's going to
say, I'll say when it says equal it means equal with ease,
you know, easily going in and out and really the problem is
bigger than equal and part of it was being imprecise because at
least one line said it couldn't be bigger. So the Gemara says
לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, leima teihavei tiyuvta d'Rav
Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua, alright let maybe that line that says it
can't be bigger that's a contradiction to Rav Huna בריה דרב יהושע.
breih d'Rav Yehoshua. So אמר לך, amar lach, he'll say back to
you, ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'amecha, according to you, אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
look, I have all the other lines in this בריתא beraisa that
support me. Look at the next case of the בריתא. beraisa. אם
היה עומד מרובה על הפרוץ אף כנגד הפרוץ מותר. im hayah omed
merubah al haparutz af k'neged haparutz mutar.
It says at the very end of the בריתא beraisa that if
it's if the partition is bigger than the break, it's all okay,
even opposite the break. It sounds like הא כפרוץ אסור ha k'farutz
assur when it is
equal it's forbidden. So almost all the lines of the בריתא beraisa
seem to indicate that when the gap is equal it's a problem,
you need the partition to be bigger. So one line you have
doesn't say that, that line is imprecise. So סיפא seifa so now
the Gemara sums it up. סיפא קשיא לרב פפא, seifa kashya l'Rav
Pappa, the last line, actually I would say three quarters of the
statements are a difficulty to Rav Pappa because they sound like equal
is no good. רישא, reisha, in the beginning part there was one
line that said greater is no good, קשיא לרב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע. kashya l'Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua. So how do you deal
with these problems? So the Gemara says סיפא לרב פפא לא קשיא,
seifa l'Rav Pappa lo kashya, no, the end is not a problem
for Rav Pappa even though the end says that you need to
be more
partition. איידי דתנא רישא פרוץ מרובה על העומד, aidi d'tana reisha parutz
merubah al ha'omed, since in the beginning we made it clear that
if the gap is bigger, that's when it's no good, תנא סיפא
עומד מרובה על הפרוץ. tana seifa omed merubah al haparutz. Therefore at
the end we say if the partition is bigger it is good.
But the guiding principle is the one line we said up above
in the beginning which is the gap is bigger. The fact that
most of the time it says equal it means equal when it
goes easily in and out which really means bigger. Bigger is the
problem. And since it's saying the gap bigger is the problem, it
says at the end when the standing part is bigger it's okay
but the key is the gap is bigger.
I'm a little confused, why wouldn't you just be consistent in your
terminology?
Yeah, so the basic point as I said before is that it
seems like in the משניות mishnayos and בריתות beraisos they were not
so much worried about the fifty-fifty case. Either they felt you can
never measure it exactly or it never really happens. So therefore they
were talking a little sloppily and they said, you know, don't make
it so if you what you know, sometimes they said don't make
it equal but really it means don't make it the real problem
is being bigger, you know, or you could say the opposite. Anyway,
the point is that there's imprecision going on here. Okay and that's
why none of it is a real proof according to either position.
רישא לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לא קשיא. reisha l'Rav Huna breih
d'Rav Yehoshua lo kashya. How about according to Rav Huna בריה דרב
יהושע? breih d'Rav Yehoshua? Why does it say in one case if
the gap is bigger it's a problem? It should have said if
the gap is
equal. No, איידי דבעי למיתני סיפא עומד מרובה, aidi d'ba'i lemitni seifa
omed merubah, since we're going to say at the end that the
standing part has to be bigger, תנא רישא פרוץ מרובה על העומד.
tana reisha parutz merubah al ha'omed. We say in the beginning if
the gap is bigger. Anyway the bottom line is that although most
of this בריתא beraisa seems to say that fifty-fifty is a problem,
seems to be a support to him, it does use at least
once a line that supports Rav Pappa and therefore every side is
able to say that there's general imprecision going on in this בריתא.
beraisa. Okay, now the Gemara says like this: בשלמא לרב פפא, bishlama
l'Rav Pappa, now the Gemara has one final argument to defend Rav
Pappa within this בריתא. beraisa. According to Rav Pappa I
understand משום הכי mishum hachi Why didn't it combine? I mean the
גמרא Gemara is saying is we had two scenarios here. We had
one well we had three scenarios, but anyway, one scenario was that
the partitions were less than three, and the other scenario was that
the partitions were from three to four, if you remember right? So
in this in this partition we said the gaps have to be
less than three, okay, because we can say לבוד. lavud. And here
we said the gaps have to be, right, less than less than
the עמוד. amud. Right? Those were the two scenarios we had, right?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says what about the case of exactly
three? So if it's exactly three, how big would the gap have
to be? So if it's exactly three, if you say like רב
פפא, Rav Pappa, that if it's exactly the same it's okay, then
exactly three falls in this category, not this. To say לבוד, lavud,
it has to be less than three. So that would not be
true if it's exactly three. If it's exactly three, the gap could
be bigger. The gap can be exactly three. Because for רב פפא
Rav Pappa the gap can be exactly equal. But for רב הונא
Rav Huna the gap has to always be a little bit smaller.
So if it's less than three the gap has to be less
than three, and if it's three the gap has to be less
than three, right? Because the gap always has to be a little
bit smaller than the עמוד. amud. So why did it put three
in category two? Three should have been in category one. Because even
in the case of exactly three, the gap has to be less
than three.
Did you want to say something before?
Well, okay, so let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says.
בשלמא לרב פפא משום הכי לא ערב להו ותני להו. Bishlema le-Rav
Pappa mishum hachi lo arev lehu ve-tani lehu. We didn't combine the
two cases of three. We didn't put three in category one. Because
three is different. Three, the gap can be three, whereas less than
three, the gap is less than three. אלא רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע לרבינא וליתנינהו? Ela Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua le-Ravina ve-listneyhu? Why
not combine them according to רב הונא? Rav Huna? כל שפחות משלושה
ושלושה, Kol she-pachos mi-shlosha ve-shlosha, less than three and three itself, צריך
שלא יהא בין זה לזה שלושה. tzerich shelo yehei bein zeh le-zeh
shlosha. It has to be less than three. Because because less than
three it has to be less because of לבוד. lavud. Three it
has to be less because any gap has to be less than
the size of the partition. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why
not put less than three and less than three in the same
category? גמרא Gemara says משום דלא דמי פסולה דרישא לפסולה דסיפא. mishum
delo dami pesula de-reisha le-pesula de-seifa. Because the reasons are different. פסולה
דרישא, Pesula de-reisha, in the first case, the whole idea of less
than three is כדי שלא יזדקר הגדי בבת אחת. kedei shelo yiztaker
hagedi be-vas achas. It's in order that it should say לבוד, lavud,
like you should say it's continuous. That's why it's significant. פסולה דסיפא
Pesula de-seifa at the end, you don't at this case category number
two you don't need לבוד. lavud. Because the reason you need less
than three is not because you need לבוד. lavud. The reason you
need less than three is שלא יהא פרוץ כעומד. shelo yehei parutz
ke-omed. Because there's a separate problem about the gaps being equal. So
it's saying you're right, they could go here, but for very different
reasons. Here the whole point of emphasizing gap less than three is
to say the principle of לבוד. lavud. Between three to four, the
principle is not לבוד. lavud. Between three to four, the principle is
that you can't have a gap too big. Okay. So therefore, in
this case three, it's true you need the gap less than three,
but not in order to say לבוד. lavud. You need the gap
less than three just for the principle that the gap can't be
too big. So it is true you could have put in the
same category, but it would have been a different reason. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to finally wrap this up. פחות
מ... Pachos mi...
okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. פחות משלושה, Pachos
mi-shlosha, now when we say in order to say לבוד lavud you
need less than three, מאני, manni, who's that going like? רבנן, Rabbanan,
the רבנן. Rabbanan. הא דאמרי אי היא דאמרי פחות משלושה אמרינן לבוד,
Ha de-amri i-hi de-amri pachos mi-shlosha amrinan lavud, less than three we
say לבוד. lavud. So שלושה לא אמרינן לבוד, shlosha lo amrinan lavud,
when you say three you don't say לבוד. lavud. So אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, let's look at the end. כל שהוא שלושה משלושה עד
ארבעה, Kol shehu shlosha mi-shlosha ad arba, that the גמרא Gemara it
makes a distinction between up to four and more than four. It
says between three and four the the partition itself is not significant
when it's standing by itself. And therefore opposite the partition is no
good. From ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim up, the partition is significant, and
therefore even if the gaps are too big, opposite the partition is
okay, it stands by itself. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says but
this idea to give significance to ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim as opposed
to three is כמאן רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, kemon Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, that's like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, דאמר
פחות מארבעה לבוד, de-amar pachos me-arba lavud, who that says that the
idea of that there's a difference between three and three and four,
and that four is a size of significance, that less than four
you say לבוד. lavud. דאי רבנן, Di Rabbanan, if it's the Rabbis,
משלושה עד ארבעה, mi-shlosha ad arba, what's the idea of this category
between three and four? שלושה וארבעה חדא היא, shlosha ve-arba chada hi,
they never distinguish between three and four. Once something is is three
or bigger, that has significance. So how do you explain that? So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so now the point though is that when
we say three or four it's the width of the partition and
it's not about לבוד, lavud, it's about a significance of a partition,
and that's what אביי Abaye answers. אמר אביי מדרישא רבנן סיפא נמי
רבנן. amar Abaye mide-reisha Rabbanan seifa nami Rabbanan.
Since the beginning is the Rabbis, the end is the Rabbis. So
meaning, yes, this is all the Rabbis. שלושה shlosha is the position
of
לבוד. lavud. ומודי רבנן דכל למשרי... U-modei Rabbanan de-chol le-mishrei... כנגדו kenegdo
that there's a different issue at stake here. You're not saying לבוד
lavud because it's more than three. Now you want to know that
it's not like the whole thing is walled because it has big
gaps. And you want to know does the partition standing by itself
have significance? So there, we're not going to use three טפחים, tefachim,
just because we say three טפחים tefachim by לבוד lavud doesn't mean
we never give significance to four טפחים. tefachim. To say that the
partition standing by itself has significance, it has to be four טפחים
tefachim big. כלו לשרי כנגדו, kolo lishrei kenegdo, if you want to
make permissible opposite the partition, so אי איכא מקום ארבעה חשיב, ei
ika makom arba'ah chashiv, if it's a space if it covers a
space of four טפחים tefachim it's significant, ואי לאו לא חשיב ve'ee
lav lo chashiv and if not not significant. And by the way,
that's true, that although we normally say that three טפחים tefachim is
לבוד, lavud, we say that for a space to be significant it
needs to be four טפחים tefachim like the minimum size of whatever
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim by
ten טפחים tefachim high, right? Anything less than four טפחים tefachim is
a מקום פטור. makom p'tor. So to be a defined significant space
it has to be four טפחים. tefachim. So what the Rabbis are
saying is, look, to say לבוד lavud right between these two things
and to make it like the gap is closed, it has to
be less than three טפחים. tefachim. But if this gap is big,
so big that it's פרוץ מרובה על העומד parutz merubah al ha'omed
and it doesn't look you can't consider it like the whole thing
is walled, and but we're asking the question is this partition standing
by itself significant? So the stuff opposite it is okay? So I
said there, three is not enough; for it to be significant standing
by itself, it has to be four טפחים. tefachim. Very reasonable answer,
and fundamentally it's the Rabbis who say you go by three by
לבוד. lavud.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, now רבא Rava says something that doesn't to
me doesn't make as much sense. מדסיפא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, mideiseifa
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, since the end is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל—no,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel since the end we talk about standing by
itself, four טפחים tefachim has significance, that's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel that gives significance to four טפחים. tefachim. So רישא
נמי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, reisha nami Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, the
beginning also is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that
says that לבוד lavud is four טפחים. tefachim. So then if that's
true, why does it say that the gaps have to be less
than three? For the following reason. וכי אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אמרינן לבוד, vechi amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel amrinan lavud, when does
he say you say לבוד? lavud? הני מילי למעלה, hani mili lemalah,
that's above, like when you want the קורה korah to be considered
connected to the wall. אבל למטה, aval lemata, when you're below and
you're dealing with a מחיצה, mechitzah, הוי ליה כמחיצה שהגדיים בוקעין בה,
hava lei kimechitzah shehagedi'im bok'in bah,
again, it's like the kid-goats can get through it, ולא אמרינן לבוד,
velo amrinan lavud, and you don't say לבוד. lavud. So remember until
now we've been talking about the other thing, about a wall that's
suspended off the ground. But even רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel that says within four you say לבוד, lavud, would say
if this is a gap that's three or bigger, it's not because
you can't call it a wall since goats can go underneath it.
Here, we're talking about a wall this way, and the gap is
this way. But nevertheless it's the same point. Even if it's between
three and four, even though you could say לבוד lavud for him
because you say לבוד lavud up to four, this is actually considered
cannot be considered a wall in any way because since the goats
can run through it this way, right not under it but through
the gaps, goats apparently have a three by three
circumference anyway you can't call it a wall. So that's what he
says, that the idea of three here is a special reason about
the goats, but the significance of four is because it's following the
position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Fine, that
ends our discussion by the whole כלאים kilayim case. I'll tell you
later because if you because then it shouldn't be based on the
way the משנה mishnah says it, that if the size of the
partition is between is less than three. Then according to that if
whatever we can talk about it later. Okay,
if you think it through it doesn't work exactly, we haven't concluded
anything. Right. Right, back to the question about פרוץ כעומד. parutz ke'omed.
So although that ברייתא braisa בני כלאים benei kilayim most of it
seemed to emphasize if it's equal it's no good, the גמרא Gemara
got out of it. So one last attempt. תא שמע, ta shema,
and here דפנות הללו, defanos hallalu,
these walls, we quoted this before as well, שרובן פתחים וחלונות, sheruban
pesachim vechalonos, if you have walls around a courtyard that's mostly
openings and windows, מותר, mutar, it's okay, ובלבד שעומד מרובה על הפרוץ,
uvilvad she'omed merubah al haparutz, as long as the majority is partition.
So the גמרא Gemara says you got a problem, it says the
majority is gaps and it's okay as long as the majority is
partition. So the גמרא Gemara says שרובן סלקא דעתך, sheruban salka dach'tach,
can you really say the majority is gaps? You said at the
end the majority has to be partition. אלא שריבה בין פתחים וחלונות,
ela sheribah bein pesachim vechalonos, it means that you have a many,
you have an increased number, you have multiple walls, gaps and windows,
מותר, mutar, it's permissible, ובלבד שעומד מרובה על הפרוץ, uvilvad she'omed merubah
al haparutz,
as long as you have more standing than partition. הא כפרוץ, ha
kefarutz, if it's equal, אסור, assur, it's forbidden. So that seems to
be clear that it's only okay if the partition is larger. תיובתא
דרב פפא תיובתא, tyufta deRav Pappa tyufta,
so it's a total contradiction to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. והלכתא, vehilchasa,
and the ruling here is כוותיה דרב פפא, kevassia deRav Pappa, like
רב פפא. Rav Pappa. The גמרא Gemara did this once before right
after saying we've completely contradicted it says and we rule like him.
So the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא והלכתא? tyufta vehilchasa? You contradicted him
and you rule like him? אין, in, yes, משום דדייקא מתניתין כוותיה,
mishum dedayka masnisin kevassia,
going back to the משנה mishnah that started the whole discussion, the
משנה mishnah sounds like him. דתנן, detnan, so you quoted this other
thing, this ברייתא braisa that said oh you have to have too
much more wall than partition. What about what the משנה mishnah said?
The משנה mishnah said
לא יהיו פרצות יתירות על הבנין, lo yihyu p'ratzos yesiros al habinyan,
you
can't have
Look, there's a
lot—the evidence is contradictory. So either there's general imprecision going on around
here and the משנה mishna and ברייתות braitot were not even thinking
about this case, or there are different opinions that are floating around.
The evidence is contradictory. And at least the implication of our משנה
mishna is like רב פפא, Rav Pappa, and that is how we
rule, that if it's equal, it's okay. All right, now we go
on to the next משנה, mishna, which is, by the way, you
should realize that we're getting into concepts that are applicable outside of
עירוב eruv as well. I mean, it is about עירוב. eruv. To
me, this also applies like by סוכה, sukkah, in other types of
cases. פרוץ כעומד, parutz ke-omed, what happens when they're exactly equal, what's
the story, you know, is a relevant question. And now the whole
idea of לבוד lavud is obviously relevant, how close to be connected.
And now we're going to get to an application of לבוד lavud
that allows you to do a very minimal type of a מחיצה.
mechitzah. Let's take a look. I should, by the way, mention, if
you look at this little תוספות, Tosafot, the הלכתא כרב פפא, hilchata
ke-Rav Pappa, תוספות Tosafot says: אין ליתמהא דהכא קיימא לן
פרוץ כעומד מותר. ein litmo'a de-hacha kaima lan parutz ke-omed mutar. Here
it says if it's equal, it's okay. ובפרק ב' דחולין מסיק דכולי
עלמא מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב. u-ve-perek bet de-Chullin masik de-chuli alma
mechtza al mechtza eino ke-rubo. There's a general question if 50/50 is
like רובו, rubo, like if you שחט shachat an animal and you
cut the trachea and the esophagus exactly 50 percent, does it count?
And תוספות Tosafot says at the end: ושמא יש לחלק בין מחיצות
לאיסור וטומאה. ve-shema yesh le-chalek bein mechitzot le-issur ve-tumah. Maybe there's a
difference. You know, every category has its different types of criteria, especially
if, look, there's another principle which is רובו ככולו, rubo ke-kulo, the
majority is like you did all of it. So there, in order
to be considered like you have all, you might need an actual
majority. You might need 51 percent. 50 percent is not enough. So
if I שחט shachat the trachea and esophagus, I might need 51
percent to be considered as if I שחט shachat the entire thing.
Okay, but here, you maybe don't have to say that it's as
if there's wall all around. If you had to say that as
if the entire thing is all wall, then you might need 51
percent. But maybe you just have to say enough of it is
wall. Like remember, for example, when you just get the corners by
the case of the well, that's also okay because it creates that
framework of the place being walled. So anyway, sometimes we actually do
require, very often we require real majority, but here, it's a different
consider the place inwalled, I should say it does not mean that
you have to claim it's as if there's wall over every gap,
and therefore 50 percent suffices. Now let's look at the next משנה
mishna which deals with even more of a minimalist wall. מקיפין שלושה
חבלים זה למעלה מזה וזה למעלה
מזה. makifin sheloshah chavalim zeh lema'ala mizeh vezeh
lema'ala mizeh. Here's a way that you can create a wall with
three strings. Now I actually have done this at times for a
סוכה sukkah when I was growing up. The סוכה sukkah I used,
you know, it had those canvas סוכות, sukkot, and the bottom would
flap and get very removed from the frame. Okay, and there's a
question, like, is, you know, how does it still considered to be
a wall if it flaps up by the wind and gets removed
from the frame? So what I did is I took strings and
ran them across, you know, those things like the metal bars from
one metal bar to the next, and the gap between each string
was less than שלושה טפחים, sheloshah tefachim, so you could say לבוד.
lavud. Okay, so it's as if it's what? That's what you do?
Right. So the metal bars. Three little bars. Now they actually have
straps that they sell with it that allow you to do it.
Anyway, I just took out some yarn or something. Now, how many
strings would you have to run in order to do that?
Only up to שלושה טפחים. sheloshah tefachim.
You have to give—the whole thing has to be up to עשרה
טפחים, asara tefachim, and if each gap is less than שלושה טפחים,
sheloshah tefachim, you would think you would need four strings, right? Why?
String number one creates gap number one. String number two, gap. String
number three, that's תשעה טפחים. tisha tefachim. Three strings is תשעה טפחים,
tisha tefachim, right? So you need עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, so you
would need four strings.
But why? In other words, the top one is only one טפח
tefach to the one before it, right? And then you have one
to the next, so it's three, six, nine. I understand. Three, three,
six, nine.
Yeah. You need it to be עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim.
No, but can't you just do like לבוד lavud at the top?
לבוד lavud has to connect to something physical. So you need on
top. If you find if your סוכה sukkah is only עשרה טפחים
asara tefachim high, you'll only need three strings. But if you're if
the סכך sechach is way higher, you need four strings. The משנה
mishna is going to do it with three strings. Let's see how
the משנה mishna does it. Okay. מקיפין שלושה חבלים זה למעלה מזה.
makifin sheloshah chavalim zeh lema'ala mizeh. You can do strings one on
top of the other. ובלבד שלא יהא בין חבל לחברו שלושה טפחים.
u-vilvad shelo yehei bein chevel le-chavero sheloshah tefachim. There can't be שלושה
טפחים sheloshah tefachim between one string and the next. שיעור חבלים ועוביין,
shiur chavalim ve-ovyan, now, the actual width of the strings themselves when
you add them all up has to be יתר על טפח, yeter
al tefach, have to combine to more than a טפח. tefach. So
if you want to do it with three strings, the way you
do it is you get thick strings. You get like straps. And
then when you add up all of the width of the strings,
you've got your extra טפח tefach that you needed. Is that clear?
So each of the gap is 2.9, so the combination is whatever
it is, is 8.7,
and the straps all are equal to one. 1.3, so then you've
now had your ten טפח. tefoch. Okay, כדי
שיהא כל עשר טפחים. k'dai sheyehey kol eser tefachim. Now מקיפין בקנים,
makifin b'kanim, you can similarly use posts, ובלבד שלא יהא בין קנה
לחברו שלושה טפחים. uvilvad shelo yehey bein kaneh l'chavero shlosha tefachim. And
now you have the gaps between the posts have to be less
than three טפחים, tefachim, and now you're doing it vertical rather than
horizontal. בשיירא דיברו. beshayara dibru.
Now all of this was by a caravan. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. That's what Rabbi Yehuda said, that normally we're going to
demand that a מחיצה mechitza be going in both directions. You can't
have it just vertical or just horizontal. But they allowed this by
a caravan because you're stuck in the middle of nowhere and it's
a special leniency. We'll see later how to define a caravan. חכמים
אומרים, chachamim omrim, but the sages say, לא דיברו בשיירא אלא בהווה.
lo dibru beshayara ela behoveh. No, they described the case of a
caravan because that was a common case. But really, this is a
general rule, and that's why we can do it by a סוכה.
sukka. You can always do just vertical or just horizontal using לבוד
lavud and you're okay. I should make a comment by the way,
which is it makes clear this case of the history of the
teaching of the משנה, mishna, that there was an early teaching that
said, here's the הלכה halacha about a caravan: you can do strings
or you can do posts. And then at a later stage, later
תנאים tannaim debated what was meant by that teaching of a caravan.
Did they mean to limit it to a caravan or did they
or were they giving that as a as a like as a
common example but really the הלכה halacha applies more broadly. So it's
a clear example of something that's referred to as like a משנה
ראשונה mishna rishona or seeing how later תנאים tannaim comment on an
earlier משנה. mishna. Actually, because it's ערב ערב פסח, erev erev pesach,
you have this in the first משנה mishna of פסחים. psachim. The
first משנה mishna of פסחים psachim says, כל מקום שאין מכניסין בו
חמץ אין צריך בדיקה, kol makom she'ein machnisin bo chametz ein tzarich
bedika, where you don't bring חמץ chametz you don't need to check.
למה אמרו lama amru or ובמה אמרו uvema amru שתי שורות במרתף.
shtei shurot bamartef. So what did they mean when they said you
had to check the two rows of the of the wine cellar?
So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it means these two rows and
בית הלל Beit Hillel says it means those two rows. Whoever said
you had to check two rows of a wine cellar? So clearly
there was an earlier teaching, and then the later תנאים tannaim are
debating what is the meaning of that earlier teaching. So here there
was an earlier teaching of a caravan, and now you have this
debate that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's only a caravan and
the rabbis say it's always the case. Okay, חכמים אומרים לא דיברו
בשיירא אלא בהווה. chachamim omrim lo dibru beshayara ela behoveh. They talked
about a caravan because that was a common
case. כל מחיצה שאינה של שתי ושל ערב אינה מחיצה. kol mechitza
she'eina shel sheti v'shel erev eina mechitza. Any מחיצה mechitza that's not
both warp and woof, horizontal and vertical, it doesn't count. דברי רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yossi b'rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Yehuda's son. Sounds
like the same thing Rabbi Yehuda said, but the what he's going
further is presumably he's denying it even by a caravan. He says
my father Rabbi Yehuda said that by a caravan it was okay,
and what I'm saying I say that it's never good if it
doesn't go both directions. וחכמים אומרים אחד משני דברים, v'chachamim omrim echad
mishnei dvarim, and the rabbis repeat their position: either vertical or horizontal,
you do not need both. Okay, very interesting. Let's see what the
גמרא gemara says. אמר רב המנונא, amar Rav Hamnuna, said Rav Hamnuna,
אמר רב, amar Rav, in the name of Rav, הרי אמרו עומד
מרובה על הפרוץ. harei amru omed meruba al haparutz. Now it's going
to combine it with the earlier
discussion. The sages said when the standing part is equal to the
broken part בשתי, besheti, when you're talking about the vertical, right, the
that's I guess the warp I guess, היינו עומד, hainu omed, it
stands, right? So we just did that when you have big gaps
even when you're not saying לבוד, lavud, as long as you have
more standing it's okay. So בערב מהו? ba'erev mahu? So Rav Hamnuna
asked, מהו? mahu? What about in the woof? Meaning what about when
you're doing the gaps are not are not vertical gaps they are
you know sort of on the vertical but they're horizontal gaps? So
בערב מאי? ba'erev mai? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, says Abaye, so
now the example would be that you have a partition, right, and
it's got let's say a part on the bottom is a is
a plank, then you have a gap, and then you have a
part on the top that's a plank. So is it enough that
you have most of it that partition has as planks the majority
of it even though it's got a gap in the middle without
saying לבוד? lavud? So let's take a look. So אמר אביי תא
שמע, amar Abaye ta shma, let's try to prove it from our
case where we needed three ropes. שלש חבלים ועובין יתר על טפח,
shalosh chavalim v'ovin yeter al tefach, שיהו הכל עשרה טפחים. sheyehu hakol
asara tefachim.
It says you have three ropes and the ropes combined have to
be more than a טפח, tefach, so combined it's ten טפחים. tefachim.
אי
איתא, i ita, if it's true that you can have a gap
big you can have a you know you don't need the whole
thing when you're going you know when you're filling up length, you
don't need the whole thing to be considered to be considered
partition, you can have gaps, so if that's true, למה לי יתר
על טפח? lama li yeter al tefach? Why did the ropes have
to equal more than a טפח? tefach? לעבד הכי. la'avid hachi.
I'll get it for you with the ropes being less than a
טפח. tefach. פחות משלושה וחבל משהו, pachot mishlosha v'chevel mashehu, less than
three and then a rope, a thin rope. פחות משלושה וחבל משהו,
pachot mishlosha v'chevel mashehu, and then you have thing that's actually three
and a rope and פחות מארבע. pachot me'arba. I'm sorry, I skipped
a
line. פחות משלושה וחבל משהו, pachot mishlosha v'chevel mashehu, פחות משלושה וחבל
משהו, pachot mishlosha v'chevel mashehu, פחות מארבע וחבל משהו. pachot me'arba v'chevel
mashehu. And then you have less than four, meaning it says I
don't get it, why don't you
just do, right,
here's your ground, okay, your first rope is 2.9, next rope 2.9.
This is 2.9, next rope 2.9, what's that, 4, 5, 5.8?
And then you have something that's like, I don't know, 4.2. So
you don't say לבוד, lavud, but
maybe you don't need to say לבוד, lavud, right?
Because you have the combination here is 5.8, so it's עומד מרובה
על הפרוץ. omed merubeh al haparutz. Who needs to say לבוד lavud
the whole way up if you can say majority partition even going
this way? Okay, right, good question, yes. So let's see what the
answer is. Okay,
so let's see what the answer is. He says, פחות מארבע
וחבל משהו. poches mi'arba v'chevel masheu. So, ותיסברא, v'tisavra, says
the גמרא. Gemara. הפחות מארבע היכא מוקימת לה? hapoches mi'arba heicha mokimt
leh? Where are you going to do this gap of 4.2? Right,
you just say make two partitions of 2.9 and then you have
a gap of 4.2 and you'll have more partition. Where exactly are
you going to put this gap? היכא מוקימת לה? heicha mokimt leh?
אי מוקימת לה תתאי, ei mokimt leh tata'ei,
if you put it on the bottom, הוי ליה מחיצה שהגדיים בוקעים
בה, havei leh mechitzah she'hagdi'im boka'im bah, then we're going to have
the problem of the goats going underneath. אי מוקימת לה עילאי, ei
mokimt leh ila'ei, if you put it on the top, אתי אוירא
דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא ומבטל ליה, ati avira dehai gisa u'dehai gisa
u'mevatel leh, then the air will nullify it. Meaning: So you're going
to basically create, if you create your 5.8 by using your לבוד
lavud tricks, right? If you've created your, whatever, your 5.8 on top
and your 4.2 on the bottom, that's no good, right? This is
your partition, because then the goats are going to go underneath. You
can't say a מחיצה mechitzah when the goats go underneath. So how
about the way I did it? You have your 5.8 here which
becomes a partition with לבוד lavud and you have your 4.2 there.
It says no, because here the rope disappears. Why does the rope
disappear? Because the airspace here and the airspace here make it insignificant,
are מבטל ליה. mevatel leh. When you say לבוד, lavud, then there's
no airspace. You've actually turned this into partition. But if you've allowed
there to be a gap and not לבוד, lavud, it's not like
you just have a bigger gap here, the rope doesn't exist at
all. You don't have anything.
Okay, so that won't work.
So you're making full walls where they don't exist and then we're
eliminating a rope where it does.
Yes, well said. Okay, אי מוקימת לה במציעאי, ei mokimt leh bemetzi'ei,
but what if you put it in the middle? Now that's, say
ah, I got a perfect way. Here's how we're going to do
it. Assuming that it's enough to have majority partition, you don't need
a hundred percent partition, why don't you have it like this? You
have your 2.9 here, your 2.9 here, and your 4.2 here. So
this is wall, this is wall, and here you have, the combination
is 5.8, is partition, more than the gap. And you don't say
that the air is מבטל ליה mevatel leh because it's not just
a rope, this is a whole real like, you know, partition. Okay,
so why don't you say that this can work? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says.
So it says,
where are we?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אי במציעאי, ei bemetzi'ei, how do
you have עומד מרובה על הפרוץ? omed merubeh al haparutz? No, but
the only way now that the partition is greater than the gap
is because it's עומד מרובה על הפרוץ משתי צדדים, omed merubeh al
haparutz mishtei tzdadim, because you combined the partition at the bottom and
the partition above to combine their 5.8, משתי רוחות, mishtei ruchot, excuse
me, from both sides. שמעת מינה, sh'mat mina, so to actually have
this case as a question, the case only begins to be a
question if עומד מרובה על הפרוץ משתי רוחות הוי עומד, omed merubeh
al haparutz mishtei ruchot havei omed, if you assume that you can
combine the two sides to say it's a majority. But we've now
been assuming that each side has to be bigger than the gap.
So you don't even have a scenario you can ask me about.
Two out of the three scenarios don't begin to even be a
case. You don't have, and the third scenario, which is your case,
is only with an assumption that you can add the sides together,
which I might not agree upon. So I don't understand your case.
I refuse to answer it because there's no good scenario that it
applies to. So the גמרא Gemara is, that's not going to stop
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says, אלא רב המנונא הכי קשיא
הכי קמיבעיא ליה. ela Rav Hamnuna hachi kashya hachi kamiba'ya leh.
Here's how רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was asking his question. Forget the
ropes. You can't prove it from our משנה mishna because you can't
have a good case in the משנה mishna that's relevant. But here's
a scenario he would be asking. דאייתי מחצלת, de'aytei machtzelet, you take
a mat, דהוי שבעה ומשהו, de'havei shiv'ah u'masheu, which was seven and
a bit, וחקק בה ג', v'chakak bah gimel, and you made an
opening of three, ושבק בה ד', v'shavak bah dalet, and you left
four, ומשהו, u'masheu, וקמה בפחות מג', v'okmah bepoches migimel,
and you put it within less than three from the ground. So
basically what you did is, forget our cases of strings. What you
did was you basically have something that is less than three from
the ground. This is 2.9. This is
7.1. Okay, so that itself should be totally fine, right? But then
what you did was you actually created an airspace up here. This
is all partition. You cut out a hole and you have the
top of the mat here. Okay, and this is three.
Joe, wait, where's the airspace?
The airspace is here. The air space is here, the air space
is here, and the mat is here in the middle. You have
a big thick partition. Okay, so in this case, okay, it equals
10, right? The
because of לבוד lavud this is this is going to be seven,
okay, but because so you have seven here, what?
You said that was 4.1.
4.1
and 2.9 is seven. Okay. So you have seven there. Okay, right?
Yeah, the whole thing is seven. Okay.
So that's your partition. Okay, and then you have a gap three,
so it's עומד מרובה על הפרוץ. omed meruba al haparutz. Now why
don't we say אתיא אוירא דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא ומבטלי, atya avira
dehai gisa u'dehai gisa u'mevatlei, right? The air space is מבטל mevatel
it on either side. So that we say because hold
on, because I did it the wrong way. I was wondering why
we didn't say that. I'm sorry, excuse me. So here's the way
we have it. This is 4.1,
this this is 2.9, that's because of לבוד lavud and this is
just a little bit, right? And this is so this is this
is your whole you had your mat, you cut out an space
like this, but you had the bottom of the mat going like
this. Okay. So in this case and this is three, alright?
So it's עומד מרובה על הפרוץ. omed meruba al haparutz. This is
4.1 and that's three, right? And there's nothing to be מבטל mevatel
because the air space there's no air space here to be מבטל,
mevatel, right? So and this is your case where this side this
side is bigger, the עומד omed here is מרובה על הפרוץ meruba
al haparutz and you have your gap. Okay. So what's the הלכה
halacha there? The whole thing is not, there's three here, you can't
say לבוד, lavud, okay, but because but it is connected to the
ground because the bottom is within three and one side is bigger
but the whole thing is not is not create is not yes?
The mat, because the picture is four not 4.1. Yeah, I
know. I just made it I just made it 4.1 in order
to combine it with the 2.9. Okay. So anyway, it says זיין
ומשהו, zayin u'mashahu, so okay, it should be 4.1. the גמרא Gemara
says בשביבי דארבע ומשהו והוקימיה פחות מג'. beshvivei d'arba u'mashahu vehokimei pachos
migimmel.
Okay, so anyway, that's our scenario. Okay, so in that case, you
have a whole three in the middle, but you can but it's
לבוד lavud to the ground, it has bigger on the top, and
are you going to say that that's good even without even though
it's not all all wall? רב אשי אמר מחיצה תלויה איבעי ליה.
Rav Ashi amar mechitzah tluya ibayei lei. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't
have an answer but at least we understand the scenario. Now רב
אשי Rav Ashi says the question was about a suspended מחיצה. mechitzah.
איבעי ליה מרב טבלא מרב, ibayei lei me'rav tavla me'rav, מחיצה תלויה
מהו שתתיר בחורבה? mechitzah tluya mahu shetatir bechorva?
If you have something that's עשרה טפחים asara tefachim but it's high
off the ground, is it okay? And again, because we know sometimes
the מחיצה mechitzah goes up, and we know hanging over water we
envision as if the מחיצה mechitzah goes down. What about dry land?
אמר ליה, amar lei, אין מחיצה תלויה מתרת אלא במים. ein mechitzah
tluya materes ela bemayim. It's only by water. קל הוא שהקילו חכמים
במים. kal hu shehikilu chachamim bemayim. It's a special דין din by
water. And again, this is the principle that even though in theory
it can go down, because the goats can go underneath it, it
can't count as a מחיצה. mechitzah. So that we have at least
an answer to. This we don't have an answer to, and that's
an interesting question. What is the story? Are you allowed gaps in
the vertical direction the same way we allow gaps in the horizontal?
I know it's already 8:30, but let's give it a few more
minutes. I'd like to get you to the bottom of the page.
Okay, and it'll really go quickly here. מקיפין בקנים. mekifin bekanim. Now
בשיירא אין ביחיד לא. beshayara in beyachid lo.
So the beginning of the משנה mishnah sounds like this is only
by a caravan. והתניא, vehatanya, but we
I mean, sorry, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says only by a
caravan not by an individual. והתניא, vehatanya, we have a ברייתא braisa
though that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda seems to be okay by an
individual. רבי יהודה אומר כל מחיצות שבת לא התירו ליחיד יותר מבית
סאתיים, Rabbi Yehuda omer kol mechitzos shabbos lo hetiru leyachid yoser mibeis
sasayim, that מחיצות mechitzos for שבת, shabbos,
these type of, you know, not real מחיצות, mechitzos, the ones like
made by strings or posts. So these things that are not 100
percent מחיצה, mechitzah, they if you're doing it for an individual, not
for a caravan, then it's only up to בית סאתיים. beis sasayim.
We talked about that on שבת, shabbos, five thousand square אמות. amos.
Bigger than that is not acceptable. But at least it works for
up to that point, up to בית סאתיים, beis sasayim, and the
משנה mishnah sounds like it didn't work at all. So the גמרא
Gemara says כדאמר רב נחמן ואיתימא רב ביבי בר אביי, k'de'amar Rav
Nachman ve'isayma Rav Bibi bar Abaye, לא נצרכה אלא ליתן להם כל
צרכן. lo nitzrecha ela liten lahem kol tzarchan. When we say it
works or it doesn't work, we mean to give you as much
space as you want. הכא נמי ליתן להם כל צרכן, hacha nami
liten lahem kol tzarchan, here too, when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
in the משנה mishnah it only works in a caravan, that means
if you want to use as much space as you
want. But it can work for an individual up to certain limits,
up to בית סאתיים. beis sasayim. So the גמרא Gemara says היכא
איתמר דרב נחמן ואיתימא רב ביבי בר אביי? heicha itmar de'rav Nachman
ve'isayma Rav Bibi bar Abaye? Where was that statement originally said that
we're talking not absolutely doesn't work, but it doesn't work without limit?
אהא דתנן, aha hadisnan, at the end of the משנה, mishnah, כל
מחיצה שאינה של שתי וערב אינה מחיצה דברי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
kol mechitzah she'eina shel shesi va'erev einah mechitzah divrei Rabbi Yose berabbi
Yehuda. Anything that's not warp and woof, two directions, is not a
מחיצה, mechitzah, these are the words of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yose berabbi Yehuda. ומי אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה הכי? umi amar
Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda hachi? Similar question like we asked about רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda father. Did רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose berabbi
Yehuda really say that it doesn't count at all? Unless it goes
in two directions, והא תניא, ve-ha tanya, we have a ברייתא, brayta,
אחד יחיד ואחד שיירא, echad yachid ve-echad shayara, whether an individual or
whether a caravan, לחבלים lechavalim can use ropes. ומה בין יחיד לשיירא?
u-mah bein yachid le-shayara? So what difference does it make? יחיד, yachid,
נותנין לו בית סאתים. nosnin lo beis sasayim. By a יחיד, yachid,
if you have a thing only made out of ropes, not a
real מחיצה, mechitza, you can only use up to the size of
a בית סאתים, beis sasayim, 5,000 square אמות. amos. שנים, shnayim, נותנין
להם בית סאתים nosnin lahem beis sasayim also, only up to 5,000
square אמות. amos. ג', gimmel, once you have
three people, נעשו שיירא, nasu shayara,
then they're a caravan, ונותנין להם בית שש. ve-nosnin lahem beis shesh.
And then they can get six, not two so six סאה, se’ah,
which is basically 15,000 square אמות. amos. דברי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
divrei Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda. But not even them it's unlimited. Right.
So וחכמים אומרים, ve-chachamim omrim, אחד יחיד ואחד שיירא, echad yachid ve-echad
shayara, there
is no difference, whether an individual whether a caravan, נותנין להם כל
צרכן. nosnin lahem kol tzarchan.
Even with this thing with ropes, it's unlimited. ובלבד, u-vilvad, the one
point is, שלא יהא בית סאתים פנוי. she-lo yehei beis sasayim panui.
That it cannot be this 5,000 square אמות amos that's completely unused.
But if they are using this space, then it's 100% okay. What
does that mean? It means that if you have all of your
equipment and all of your tents are in a certain space, there
can't be a big unused space bigger than בית סאתים. beis sasayim.
But if you want to use the space and you have, then
you can use it as big as it wants to be. So
anyway, what do you see? You see that although in the משנה
mishna רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda said if it
doesn't go in both directions, it's completely not good whether for individuals
or for a caravan, he doesn't really mean completely not good. He
means you don't have unlimited usage. So אמר רב נחמן ואיתימא רב
ביבי בר אביי, amar Rav Nachman ve-isayma Rav Bibi bar Abaye, לא
נצרכה אלא ליתן להם כל צרכן. lo nitzrecha ela liten lahem kol
tzarchan.
When the משנה mishna says it's no good, it means unlimited usage.
But if you want to limit the use, then the ropes will
work. For a יחיד yachid it will work to give you בית
סאתים, beis sasayim, and for a שיירא shayara three times as much,
that it'll be okay with limits. So the same with his father
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. When he said they only spoke about a
שיירא shayara not for an יחיד, yachid, it means unlimited it doesn't
work for an יחיד yachid but with limits it does work. וחכמים
ve-chachamim say that it's unlimited and you can always use the ropes
and the strings and the posts, and that's how we פסקן. pasken.
Okay.